ESTHER SANDERS

SOFTWARE DEVELOPER

804.901.4165 esthernaomi.violin@gmail.com https://www.linkedin.com/in/esthersanders23/ https://github.com/esthersanders

ABOUT

I've worked as a violinist and teacher for over a decade and was drawn to software development because of the many similarities to music. I love learning, continually refining skills, problem solving, and attention to detail. I have many years of experience self starting, dissecting large problems into smaller parts, and communicating complex ideas.

TECHNICAL EXPERIENCE

Nashville Software School

NSS is a six-month intensive, full-time software development bootcamp focusing on HTML, CSS, Javascript, React and server-side fundamentals with Python and Django.

- Single-page application development with React and with a focus on modern ES6+ Javascript features and modular code
- Project management with issue tickets and GitHub Projects
- Database planning by building entity relationship diagrams (ERD) to define relationships with an emphasis on maintaining a flat data structure
- Utilized vanilla JavaScript (ES6), and React.js to create single page dynamic web applications using full CRUD functionality
- Styled applications using CSS, Bootstrap, reactstrap, and Material UI
- Completed 6 group project sprints while fully remote, comfortable with Slack, Zoom, GitHub Projects, and wireframes for group communication and collaboration

PROJECTS

BetterMe

BetterMe is an app for users to create and track many habits simultaneously, with a visual representation of their progress. Built using the React framework for JavaScript, it also utilizes CSS, reactstrap, and Material UI. Information about the habits users create is stored using JSON server and includes full CRUD functionality.

https://github.com/esthersanders/BetterMe

Group Project: Nutshell

Nutshell is a social application for users to use to organize their daily tasks, events, news articles, and interact with other users. I worked with three other team members to create this app. My contributions include the Tasks component, the logout button, the New Friend Form, and the Alien themed CSS styling. https://github.com/NSS-Day-Cohort-42/nutshell-alien-abductees

EXPERIENCE

Nashville Symphony / Section Violin

January 2012 - PRESENT, Nashville, TN

• Learn and perform new repertoire every week while quickly adapting to changes by listening and adjusting to colleagues in real time

Lipscomb University / Violin Instructor

August 2020 - PRESENT, Nashville, TN

• Teaching individual private lessons to music majors

- Tailoring learning objectives, repertoire, and technical studies to each student's individual needs based on their past training and future goals
- Emphasizing the fundamentals of sound production and problem solving at every opportunity, in a variety of contexts, to encourage the transfer of important concepts to new situations
- Empowering students to be their own teacher by cultivating sharper listening skills to identify problems, then facilitating an awareness of how to solve problems through small steps

Musician/Teacher Freelance

2010-PRESENT

- Performed with many small and large ensembles as a section member (Austin Symphony, The Glimmerglass Festival) and as a leader (Austin Opera)
- Recording sessions for soundtracks, artists, bands
- Regularly record and perform while sight-reading (no prior rehearsals) or with minimal rehearsal
- Accustomed to working on a short timeline with a high level of focus
- Maintained a private violin studio of 20-30 students of all ages and levels. Responsibilities included scheduling, lesson planning, creating payment plans, implementing a studio policy to set expectations for students and parents, organizing student recitals at the end of each semester
- Instructor of violin at four colleges- Texas Lutheran University, Concordia University, Austin Community College, Lipscomb University. Individual and group lessons. Responsible for grades, repertoire choices, collaborating with other faculty, leading group classes with students at a wide variety of proficiency levels

EDUCATION

Nashville Software School / Full Stack Software Development July 2020-January 2021

The University of Texas at Austin / Master of Music, Violin Performance 2012-2014

Vanderbilt University / Bachelor of Music, Violin Performance 2006-2010